Guide to the Women's Environment and Development Organization records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Women's Environment and Development Organization Records,
1980-2006
[Bulk Dates: 1994-1998].
Women's Environment & Development Organization.
16.5 linear feet (39 document boxes and 1 oversized folder).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
5685941
The records of the Women's Environment and Development Organization (WEDO) document its political advocacy for women’s equality in formulating global policy, and highlights founders New York State Representative, Bella Abzug (1920-1988) and feminist activist, Miriam "Mim" Kelber (1922-2004).
Historical Note
The Women's Environment and Development Organization (WEDO), is a non-governmental organization (NGO) founded by former New York State Representative Bella Abzug (1920-1988) and Miriam "Mim" Kelber (1922-2004), among others. Its goal is to advocate for women's equality in global policy.
Abzug and Kelber were high school friends and classmates at Hunter College in New York City. Both were feminists and activists from their early years. Kelber was the New York news editor for the labor-syndicated Federated Press from 1943-1955 while Abzug, after graduating from Columbia University Law School in 1947, became one of a few privately practicing female lawyers. Abzug and Kelber (among others), co-founded the "Women Strike for Peace" campaign, one of the first groups of the 1960s to protest the Vietnam War.
When Bella Abzug was elected to the New York State House of Representatives in 1971, Kelber became her executive assistant and speech writer until Abzug left office in 1978. Kelber also chaired the National Women's Political Caucus media committee. President Jimmy Carter appointed Abzug to the chair of his National Advisory Committee for Women, and Kelber served as its policy consultant and writer. When Carter fired Abzug as head of the advisory committee in 1979 after it actively criticized Carter for budget cuts, both women left the administration. Together they went on to establish the organization that would eventually become WEDO: the Women USA Fund., Inc.
Women USA Fund was incorporated in 1980 as an action and information network for the "woman who wants to help win equality and justice for all women." The Fund established a 24-hour hotline for action alerts, lobbied for women's representation in Washington, DC government, and sponsored and organized educational forums, symposiums, and conferences. In 1985, the Women USA Fund developed a proposal (written by Kelber) to establish the non-partisan Women's Foreign Policy Council. According to the original proposal, the Council aimed to enhance the visibility of women in public debate formulation and the conduct of American foreign policy on a variety of issues; encourage the opening of national and international political roles for women as foreign policy leaders; and to serve as a "Women's 'Shadow' State Department" in order to propose alternative, peace-oriented policies and analyses of constructive solutions to world problems. A major goal of this fledgling organization was to develop and write the first-ever comprehensive directory of women foreign policy specialists and organizations working in the realm of International Affairs. Abzug served as the policy chair of the directory and the group, while Kelber served as its Editorial Director (a position that she would later assume at WEDO as well). The Women's Foreign Policy Council Directory was published in 1987 and included a picture, areas of expertise, recent professional experience, professional appointments and memberships, and contact information. Additional listings included contacts for female members of the U.S. Congress, foreign heads of state, organizations working on war and peace issues, United Nations and Non-Governmental Organization (NGO) leaders and other contacts. The Council also established an aggressive public relations campaign and aimed to sponsor public debates on major issues with both male and female participants.
The Women's USA Fund began planning a major conference in 1990 under the title, the "World Women's Congress on a Healthy Planet.” The project was launched under the name of the "Women's Environment and Development Organization" or "WE-DO." The Congress was held in Miami, Fl. in 1991 and prepared the way for women's involvement at the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development (UNCED Earth Summit, 1992, Rio de Janeiro) by producing a Women's Action Agenda 21 to help shape the dialogue of the UNCED from a woman's perspective. While closely related to the United Nations' own “21st century agenda” known as Agenda 21 (a sprawling, 900-page all-encompassing action document) produced at the Rio summit, WEDO's Women's Action Agenda 21 provided a uniquely woman-centric perspective regarding the environment, poverty, war, and disease. The Miami Congress itself became known as a major event in women's international organizing history and established a strong network of women working on environmental and development issues.
In 1994, the Fund published Women and Government: New Ways to Political Power, edited by Kelber. This work, sponsored by the Stanley Foundation, was a survey of six European countries analyzing the success of their women's movements and the advancement of women in their governments, and how these successes could be applied to American politics. On January 27, 1995, Women USA Fund, Inc., officially changed its name to the Women's Environment and Development Organization.
WEDO's mission was similar to the Women USA Fund, Inc., in that WEDO would serve as an organ to disseminate general information to the public, though WEDO established a broader mission to encourage academics and other communities to research and write on women's policy issues, provide technical assistant and training to empower women and develop leadership skills, and like the Women USA Fund, to sponsor conferences and symposiums. Beginning in 1991, WEDO organizers served on the United Nation's Commission on the Status of Women, in preparation for the UN's Fourth Woman's Conference (1995), held in Beijing, China. WEDO worked after the conference to disseminate conference information, track government and UN commitments, hone the language of the Conference's “Platform for Action,” lobby politicians, and attend follow-up sessions (Beijing +5, 2000). In 1996, WEDO developed the “Contract with Women of the USA” campaign as a counter to Newt Gingrich's “Contract with America.” The WEDO Contract adopted key elements of the Beijing Platform for Action and applied them to American women as a feminist response to the Republican Contract.
After Abzug's death in 1998, WEDO helped to establish a memorial fund in her name, the Abzug Leadership Award. Kelber left her position as editorial director at WEDO the same year and continued to work with WEDO as a non-staff member. Mim Kelber died in 2004 and was survived by her husband, AFL-CIO leader, Harry Kelber, and daughters Karli and Laura.
The organization has consistently been involved with world politicians, activists, feminists, and other notable and "ordinary" women who have helped with WEDO projects or served on the Board of Directors. Prime among these women is Wangari Maathai, a WEDO board member and co-founder, who was the first president of the African Union (2005) and Nobel Prize (2004) recipient "for her contribution to sustainable development, democracy and peace." WEDO continues its work on behalf of women in the memories of Bella Abzug and Mim Kelber.
Scope and Content
The records of the Women's Environment and Development Organization (WEDO) document its political advocacy for women's equality in formulating global policy, and highlights founders New York State Representative, Bella Abzug (1920-1988) and feminist activist, Miriam "Mim" Kelber (1922-2004).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into six series. The files are arranged in alphabetical order.
Series I: Women's Environment and Development Organization (WEDO), 1980-2006
Subseries I.1: Administrative Files, 1983-2000
Subseries I.2: Board of Directors, 1994-2000
Subseries I.3: Women USA Fund, Inc., 1984-1994
Subseries I.4: Subjects, 1980-1994
Subseries I.5: Conferences, Campaigns, and Organizations, 1990-2000
Series II: Women's Foreign Policy Council, 1985-1990
Series III: United Nations, 1972-2000 [Bulk Dates: 1994-1996]
Subseries III.1: Conferences, Campaigns, and Organizations, 1979-2000 [Bulk Dates: 1994-1996]
Subseries III.2: World Women's Conference--Beijing, China, 1989-2000 [Bulk Dates: 1994-1996]
Series IV: Abzug, Bella, 1984-2000 [Bulk Dates: 1992-1998]
Series V: Publications and Printed Matter, 1974-2000 [Bulk Dates: 1994-1998]
Subseries V.1: Women's Environment and Development Organization, Women's USA Fund, Inc., and Women's Foreign Policy Council, 1987-2002
Subseries V.2: Other Organizations, 1974-2000
Subseries V.3: Oversized Printed Matter, 1977-1997
Series VI: Audio Visual Material 1991-2006
Subjects
Earth Summit Watch (Organization); Women's Environment & Development Organization.; Women's Foreign Policy Council (U.S.); Women USA Fund, Inc.; United Nations Conference on Environment and Development (1992 :--Rio de Janeiro, Brazil); World Conference on Women (1995 :--Beijing, China); World Conference to Review and Appraise the Achievements of the United Nations Decade for Women (1985 :--Nairobi, Kenya); World Women's Congress for a Healthy Planet.; Abzug, Bella S., 1920-1998.; Kelber, Mim.; Maathai, Wangari.; Siegel, Beatrice.; Sustainable development.; Women in sustainable development.; Agenda 21.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library Reading Room. Please consult the Rare Book and Manuscript Library for further information.
This collection has no restrictions except for one folder. This folder is located in Box 12, Folder 5 and is restricted until 2035.
Acquisition
This collection was donated to the rare Book and Manuscript Library in three donations. The first and largest was donated by Mim Kelber in 2003.
DVDs, VHS tapes, and books were donated by Joan Nixon and Harry Kelber in 2006.
DVDs, VHS tapes, and books were donated by Leandra Zarnow in 2007.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Women's Environment and Development Organization (WEDO), undated, 1980-2006 [Bulk Dates: 1994-1998]
  Series I primarily contains WEDO organizational records and is divided into five subseries. The series holds administrative files of WEDO and its predecessor, the Women USA Fund, Inc., Board of Directors minutes and correspondence, subject files, and numerous materials including correspondence, reports, and brochures gathered from conferences attended by WEDO, campaigns organized by others in which WEDO contributed, and other organizations with which WEDO collaborated in some fashion.
  - Subseries I.1: Administrative Files 1983-2000
    The administrative files of WEDO are arranged in alphabetical order. Though primarily administrative files, the subseries also contains several of Mim Kelbers' notebooks and articles written by her on behalf of WEDO. Outlines, notes, and interviews on WEDO history may also be in this series (two microcassettes of these interviews may be found in Subseries V.1) as well as correspondence with and on behalf of Wangari Maathai's 1998 run for the presidency of Kenya. The correspondence is primarily from her daughter, Wanjira, but does contain letters from Wangari Maathai herself.
    - General, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General--Notebooks, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Action Plans, undated, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Annual Reports, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Annual Reports (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Audit Correspondence, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Breast Cancer, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Breast Cancer, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Boutros-Ghali, Boutros--Correspondence and Speech, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Budget, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Budget Projections, post-Beijing, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Case Studies, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Clinton Administration Women's Programs and Commitments, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    - Computer Committee, 2000 September 25 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Contract with Women of the USA
      - General, undated, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - General, undated, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
      - Brooklyn Women's Coalition, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Fundraising, 1996-1999 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Houston Anniversary, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - National Action Agenda for Women Teleconference, Brooklyn, NY, 1996 September 28 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Schneider, Karen, Media Correspondence, undated, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Welfare, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Wolfe, Leslie Budget Correspondence, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and Memos, undated, 1994-2000 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
    - Davis, Susan, "WEDO and the Public Advocacy Agenda in Creating Sustainable Human Development,"St. John's Law Review, v. 69:351, 1995 November (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Elections
      - 1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - 2000 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Engendering Local Agenda 21 Workshop Report, 2000 July (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Events
      - General, 1995, 1998, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence and Invitations--Susan Davis, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence, Flyers and Memos, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
      - Attended by WEDO Personnel, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Not Attended by WEDO Personnel, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Financial Statements,1995-1998 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Foundation Correspondence--A-Z, 1987-1997 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Foundation Correspondence--A-Z, 1987-1997 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Friedrich-Naumann-Stiftung Foundation, 1991-1997 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Funding File, undated, 1991-1996 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    - Funding Proposals, 1991-1993 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
    - Grants and Grant Reports
      - 1993-1995 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - 1996-2000 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
    - Habitat II in Istanbul
      - Huairou Commission Follow-up, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Report and Issues Paper, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - History of WEDO
      - Background Material, undated, 1983-1991 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Interviews, undated, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Integrated Advocacy and Monitoring Program, 1998 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Kelber, Mim--Articles (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - "Daughters of Mother Earth, The," New Directions for Women, 1989 July/August
      - "For Women of the world, the time has come to break forth toward power," Perspectives, Earth Times,1993 June 30
      - Letter to Mark Shields, Washington Post,undated
      - "'Old Boys' Network Still Alive and Well at the United Nations," Der Uberblick,undated
      - "Women: Just Another 'Special' Interest Group?," unknown publication, undated
      - "Women's Environment and Development Organization," Institutions, Environment Newsletter,1994 October
    - Kelber, Mim and Bella Abzug Color Photograph Photocopies, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Latin America Project Proposal, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - "Lighting the Path to Progress"--Commission on Sustainable Development WEDO Report, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Maathai, Wangari and Wanjira--Correspondence, Memos and Articles, 1997-1998 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - McArthur Foundation Grant
      - 1992 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - 1996-1998 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Media Correspondence, 1992-1995 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Media Plan, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Neier, Yvette--Red Rose Collection Correspondence, undated, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Research Papers and Requests, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Retreat, 1995 November (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - "Special Global Reflection: Charting Strategic Directions for the 21st Century" Conference, 1998 June 20-22 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Speech Material, undated, 1980s-1990 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Staff Meeting, June 6, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - State Organizing--Other Active States, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Target State Organizing Correspondence and Organizers Lists
      - General, undated, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - California, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Florida and Illinois, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Iowa, Kansas, Maine, and Maryland, 1995-1997 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Massachusetts, Michigan, and Minnesota, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - New York, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - North Carolina, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Ohio, Oklahoma, Oregon, and Pennsylvania, 1996-1997 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Texas and Utah, 1996-1997 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Tax Burden Analysts Report and Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Transnational Corporations (TNC) Primer, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Whistle-stop Campaign to Washington/Torch Relay Project, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Women's Global Strategies Meeting--Glen Cove, NY, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Women in Decision-Making Experts List and Proposal, 1993-1994 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Women's History Month, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Women's International Advocacy Program Funding Proposal, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Zill, Anne--Correspondence and Memos, 1995-1996 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Zill, Anne--Correspondence and Memos, 1995-1996 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Subseries I.2: Board of Directors, 1994-2000
    This subseries includes Board of Directors, Executive Committee and Steering Committee minutes, agendas, correspondence and memos pertaining to the governance and activities of WEDO.
    - General, undated, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Board Meetings, 1990-1996 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Board Reports and Calendars, 1993 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and Memos, 1998-1999 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Directors Meeting
      - 1994 November 28 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - 1995 November 1 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - 1996 January 12-14 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - 1997 April 20-21 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - 2000 March 11 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Directors and International Steering Committee Meeting, 1996 January 12-14 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Executive Committee Meeting
      - 1996 September 29 (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - 1996 November 23-24 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - 1999 October 8 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - 2000 February 4-5 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - 2000 September 7-8 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Post-Board Meeting, Addenda, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      [Restricted until 2035]
    - Steering Committee Meeting
      - 1992 October 19 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - 1993 May 6-7 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - 1994 November 28 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Subseries I.3: Women USA Fund, Inc., 1984-1994
    Women USA Fund, Inc., as a subseries, overlaps slightly with the records of WEDO. Primarily the materials pertain to the early years of WEDO in regards to funding proposals, financial statements, the Fund's work with the Democratic National Committee in 1984, and the development of an environmental-themed t-shirt design that incorporated the autographs of famous female personalities. In 1990, Women USA Fund, Inc., began planning for their World Women's Congress for a Healthy Planet symposium. The Fund established WEDO as the project arm of the Women's Congress. As such, files regarding the Women's Congress are located in this subseries. Official incorporation change to WEDO did not occur until 1995, though the greater majority of WEDO records prior to 1995 are located in Subseries I.1.
    - By-Law Change, 1993-1994 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Democratic National Committee, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Family of Earth Pledge of Allegiance Copyright and Trademark, 1989-1990 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Financial Report, 1992 (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Financial Statements, 1990-1994 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Funding File, 1980s (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Opinion Survey, undated (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Original Congress Proposals, undated, 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Women in the Environment T-Shirt, circa 1990 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Women's Telethon Proposal, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - World Women's Congress for a Healthy Planet, Miami, FL
      - General, 1989-2001, (3 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 4-6)
      - Finances, 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Testimonies and The Nation Abstracts, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Transcripts, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Proposals, 1991-1992 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Subseries I.4: Subjects, 1980-1994
    This subseries contains material that was collected on specific subjects of interest to both Mim Kelber and/or the WEDO organization. Subjects include women in national politics; economic and environmental issues; the Balkans/Kosovo conflict of 1999; Africa; abortion and reproductive rights; gender balance, and the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA).
    - Abortion, Population, and Reproductive Rights, undated, 1985-1995 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Africa, undated, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Balkans/Kosovo Crisis, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Gender Balance, Issues and Justice, 1995-1996 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), 1997 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Project Vote/Election 1980, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 7-8)
    - Religious Right, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - United States
      - Women in the Federal Government, 1996 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Women's Vote and Electoral Reform, 1994-1997 (Box 15, Folder 2-3)
    - Women and Economic Issues, 1996 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Women and Global Energy and Environment Issues, undated, 1993-1994 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Subseries I.5: Conferences, Campaigns and Organizations, 1990-2000
    WEDO attended numerous conferences, helped coordinate multiple campaigns, and interacted with many non-United Nations and non-governmental organizations to achieve their goals of engendering issues on International and National platforms. The records contained in this subseries document their work with or attendance at, a wide variety of events and work with these organizations. The materials do not regard WEDO's work with United Nations-sponsored meetings such as the Earth Summit and Agenda 21, the Beijing Conference and its Platform for Action, nor Rio +5 or Beijing+5, though some materials contain references to these United Nations forums. For materials on these conferences, please see Subseries III.1: United Nations Conferences, Campaigns, and Organizations.
    - General Printed Material, 1998-2002 (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - "50/50 by 2005 Women in Government; Get the Balance Right!"
      - General, undated, 1990-2000 (Box 38, Folder 6-7)
      - George Dean, Executive Director, 1990-1992 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Printed Material, 2000-2001 (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - 180 Days/180 Ways Women's Action Campaign, 1995 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Action for a Common Future (Bergen Conference)
      - General, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 3-4)
      - Addresses and Statements, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 5-6)
    - Canada Caribbean Gender Equity Fund Proposal, 1998 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Centre for Our Common Future, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Council of Presidents/White House Interagency Council on Women, 1996 (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
    - Earth Summit Interviews and Resources, undated, 2000 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Expo 2000 Hanover, Germany, 1998 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Fawcett Society, 1997 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Feminist Majority Expo (Washington, DC), February 2-4, 1996 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Forum Internazionale, "Le donne nell'economia globale: Opportunità, Innovazione, Democrazia Economica," 1997 October (Box 17, Folder 7)